Paul-Henry Leemann

Researcher in Pure Mathematics

Université de Neuchâtel
Institut de mathématiques
2000 Neuchâtel, Suisse

Paul-Henry.Leemann@unine.ch

www.leemann.website



Personal Information

Date of Birth April 12, 1987 Citizenship Switzerland

Main areas of research

My research interests lie in the intersection of geometric and combinatorial group theory, graph theory and symbolic dynamic. I am particularly interested in groups acting on rooted trees and their (weakly) maximal subgroups, limits and coverings of (Schreier) graphs, rigidity phenomenon in Cayley and Schreier graphs and graphs associated to dynamical systems.

Employment

- Starting August Xi'an Jiaotong-Liverpool University, Suzhou, China, Assistant Professor, in Department of Pure Mathematics.

 Currently postponed due to the pandemy.
 - 2021–2022 **Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland**, Scientific collaborator, in Institut de mathématiques.
 - 2020–2021 **Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland**, *Post-Doc*, in Institut de mathématiques, with Alain Valette.
 - 2018–2020 **ENS-Lyon, France**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

 Post-Doc Labex MILYON
 - 2016–2018 **ENS-Lyon, France**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

 Early Postdoc.Mobility grant supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation

Education

- 2011–2016 **Université de Genève, Switzerland**, *Ph.D. in Mathematics*, "On Subgroups and Schreier Graphs of Finitely Generated Groups", advisor: Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda. Mention très bien
- 2013–2014 Université de Genève, Switzerland, Basic Certificate of Didactic in Mathematics and in Educational Science.
- 2009–2011 **Université de Genève, Switzerland**, M. Sc. in Mathematics, Master-thesis: "Caractères irréductibles des groupes de Coxeter finis", advisors: Pierre de la Harpe and Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda. grades: 6/6 (Master-thesis) and 5.7/6 (courses)
- 2006–2009 Université de Genève, Switzerland, B. Sc. in Mathematics.

Publications

- 1. Wreath products of groups acting with bounded orbits, with G. Schneeberger. Accepted in l'Enseignement mathématiques (2022). https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.08001
- 2. Property FW and wreath products of groups: a simple approach using Schreier graphs, with G. Schneeberger. Accepted in Expositiones Mathematicae (2022). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.03817
- 3. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms: the case of infinite groups, with M. de la Salle. Annales Henri Lebesgue Vol. 5 (2022). https://doi.org/10.5802/ahl.118
- 4. Up to a double cover, every regular connected graph is isomorphic to a Schreier graph. Bulletin of the Belgian Mathematical Society Simon Stevin Vol. 28, Issue 3 (2022). https://doi.org/10.36045/j.bbms.210416
- 5. Finitely generated subgroups of branch groups and subdirect products of just infinite groups, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Izvestia: Mathematics Vol. 85 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1070/IM9101
- 6. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms, with M. de la Salle. Journal of Algebraic Combinatorics Vol. 53 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10801-020-00956-1
- 7. Schreier graphs: Transitivity and Coverings. International Journal of Algebra and Computation Vol. 26, Issue 1 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1142/S021819671650003X
- 8. Weakly maximal subgroups in regular branch groups, with K. Bou-Rabee and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Algebra Vol. 455 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jalgebra.2016.02.009
- 9. Lamplighter groups, de Bruijn graphs, spider-web graphs and their spectra, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical Vol. 49, Number 20 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1088/1751-8113/49/20/205004

Preprints

- 10. Most rigid representation and Cayley index of finitely generated groups, With M. de la Salle. (2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.02326
- 11. Subgroup induction property for branch groups, with D. Francoeur. (2020). https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.13310
- 12. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. (2020). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.06399

Prizes and Grants

- 2021–2022 "Group theory, topology and dynamics: Russian-Swiss collaboration", 2 years collaboration
- 2018-2020 Labex MILYON Postdoc grant
- 2016–2018 Early Postdoc. Mobility grant supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation
 - 2016 Vacheron Constantin prize for the best thesis in mathematics, *Université de Genève*, Switzerland

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

Conferences organisation

- June 2022 Self-similarity of groups, trees and fractals, co-organizer, 30 May-3 June, Institut Henri Poincaré, France
- Octobre 2021 Kervaire seminar "Baum-Connes conjecture", co-organizer, 24-29 Octobre, Les Diablerets, Switzerland
 - March 2013 Kervaire seminar "Géométrie des groupes 2013", local organizer, 10-15 March, Les Diablerets, Switzerland

Talks (selected)

Conferences:

- August 2021 World Of Group Craft, inline conference, Wreath product of groups acting with bounded orbits.
 - June 2018 Trees Dynamics and Locally Compact Groups, Heinrich Heine University, Dusseldörf, Germany. Profinite completion of weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups.
- January 2017 Rencontre GAMME, Sète, France. Weakly maximal subgroups of the Grigorchuk group. Existence and construction of IRS.
- November 2014 Paroles aux jeunes chercheurs en géométrie et dynamique, GDR Platon, Université de Bordeaux, France. A criterion for the transitivity of Schreier graphs.
 - June 2014 Workshop in Algebra and Geometry, University of Bern, Switzerland. Transitivity of Schreier graphs and strongly simple groups.
- September 2013 Geometric and Analytic Group Theory, Ventotene, Italy. $Transitivity\ of\ Schreier\ graphs.$

Seminars:

- May 2021 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, Université de Genève, Switzerland. *Produit en couronne et groupes agissant avec des orbites bornées*.
- April 2021 Algebra Seminar, Lincoln University, United-Kingdom. Branch groups and the subgroup induction property. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/subgroupinduction.pdf
- April 2021 Séminaire Géométrie, Algèbre, Algèbre d'opérateurs, Université de Clermont-Ferrand, France. Graphes de Cayley avec peu d'automorphismes. Slides (in French): http://www.leemann.website/slides/clermont-ferrand.pdf
- March 2021 Group theory seminar, ENS, Paris, France. De Bruijn graphs, spider web graphs and Lamplighter groups. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/bruijn.pdf
- February 2021 Symmetry in Newcastle, University of Newcastle, Australia. Rigidity of Cayley graphs. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/newcastle.pdf
- November 2020 Colloque du département de mathématiques, Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland.

 Groups and graphs: rigidity phenomena. Slides (in French): http://www.leemann.
 website/slides/rigidity.pdf
 - March 2020 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, Université de Genève, Switzerland. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/weaklymaximal.pdf
 - October 2019 Séminaire de Géométrie, Groupes et Dynamiques, ENS Lyon. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.
 - July 2019 Séminaire Darboux, Montpellier, France. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.

Teaching Experiences

- 2020–2021 In Neuchâtel:
 - 1x "Branch groups", a 6 hours mini-course for doctoral students
- 2016–2020 In ENS Lyon:
 - 3x Teaching assistant of "Coverings and fundamental groups" (master)
 - 1x Teacher of "Introduction to LATEX" (3rd year class)
- 2011–2016 Teaching assistant at the University of Genève:
 - 1x Advanced course on Combinatorics (master)
 - 3x Algebra II: groups, rings, fields, Galois theory (2nd year class)
 - 2x Algebra I: linear algebra (1st year class)
 - 1x Analysis I: basics of logic and set theory, real analysis (1st year class)
 - 1x General mathematics: 1st year class for students of other departments
 - 1x Tutoring for first year students
- 2006–2011 Private tutor in mathematics for high school students

Scientific popularization

- 2018 MATHαLYON: interactive workshop in Junior High School, Lyon, France
- 2015 Facilitator at the "Science's night", Genève, Switzerland
- 2012–2014 Facilitator at the University "Open Day", Genève, Switzerland
- 2011–2012 Mathematics' facilitator in Junior High School and High School classes, Genève, Switzerland
- 2009–2010 Mentor in the "boussole" curriculum (one week of immersion in the mathematics' department, for High School's students), Genève, Switzerland

Memberships in panels and scientific reviewing activities

I have been an external expert for the OPUS-21 grant funding scheme of the National Science Centre Poland.

I have been a referee for the following journals: Journal of Algebra, International Journal of Algebra and Computation, L'enseignement mathématiques, Expositiones Mathematicae, Journal of Algebra and its Applications.

Languages

French: native English: fluent German: basics

Computer skills

(IA)T_EX and TikZ: advanced HTML/CSS:basics GAP: basics